Hi, I'm Dr. Michael Trezella
and this is the OMM lab
number 33 pre-lab lecture
for palpation of the cranial
strain patterns, chondylar
decompression, and lifts.
Before you get started
watching this lecture,
you need to make sure
you review all of the
material on this slide
because this lecture
builds upon what you
learned in the previous
material you've gotten
so far this semester.
These are the session
objectives. You can pause
here and read them if
you'd like to, but I'm
going to move on to the
main part of the lecture.
These next two
slides are going to
review the the strain
patterns that you'll be going
over. This slide here goes
over the physiologic strain
patterns, so you should
be able to look at this
and just review what was
taught in Dr. Yao's lecture.
And this chart here
reviews the non-physiologic
strain patterns as discussed
in Dr. Yao's lecture.
So to quickly review,
when you have your hands
in the vault hold on the
patient's head or the vault
contact as we call it,
During the flexion
phase, your hands are
going to spread apart
slightly, your fingers
are going to spread
apart, and you're going
to feel like your hands
and your fingers are
moving more caught at
or towards the feet.
During the extension phase,
your hands are going to
slightly come together, your
fingers are going to come
together, and you're going
to feel like your hands
and fingers are moving more
cephalad towards the head.
If somebody has a right
side bending rotation,
it's going to feel like
your right fingers and
your right hand are
moving towards the feet,
caudad, and your left
fingers and hands are
going to be moving towards
the head or cephalad.
The right fingers are
going to be spreading
apart and your left hand
fingers are going to
be narrowing. If you
have a left side bending
rotation, the opposite
is going to occur.
You're going to have a,
the left hand is going
to, the fingers are
going to spread out and
move towards the patient's
feet and the right
hand fingers are going
to come together and feel
like they're moving
towards you or cephalad.
in a right torsion,
you're going to feel like
your right index finger
is going to be coming
up towards you, and the
right pinky is going
to be moving more towards
the patient's feet.
And the opposite's happening
with the left hand.
The left index finger is
moving towards the feet,
and the right one is
coming towards your head.
And the opposite's
occurring in a left torsion.
like your left hand is
twisting so that your index
finger is coming up
towards you and your left
pinky is moving towards
the feet and the
opposites occurring
with the right hand
with the non-physiologic
strain patterns you have
a right lateral strain the
left lateral strain and
a superior shear and an
inferior shear so with
the right lateral strain
the way we're describing
it, you're going to feel
like your index fingers for
both hands are going to
be moving towards the
left and your pinkies are
moving towards the right.
In a left lateral strain
you're going to feel
like your index fingers are
moving towards the right
and your pinkies are
moving towards the left.
This is different from
what you expect when
you're naming it but
remember we're naming the
strain pattern for the
direction of the basi
sphenoid not the
direction of the fingers.
In a superior shear what
you're going to be feeling
is basically both hands the
index fingers are going to
be moving towards the feet
and the pinkies are moving
towards the head in a
superior shear, and in an
inferior shear, the index
fingers are moving towards the
head, and the pinkies are
moving towards the feet.
The techniques we're
going to be doing
in this lab are
chondral decompression,
frontal lift, parietal lift,
zygomatic lift,
and nasion spread.
We're not going to be
discussing how to perform
these techniques now
during this lecture, but
we will be discussing
and demonstrating it in
the lab and you also need
to watch the lab videos
before you go to lab
to prepare yourself to
be able to learn these
techniques in the lab.
There are many indications
for treating patients
with osteopathic cranial
manipulative medicine.
This slide has some of the
indications listed but there
are many others that that
you can you can find as
well you can pause here and
read the list if you'd like
as far as contraindications go
well first of all
patient must consent
if they don't consent
you can't do it
there has to be
some sort of somatic
dysfunction for the most part
any acute bleeds in the head
cerebrovascular accidents
you want to be careful
you pretty much consider
it as an absolute
contraindication if
anybody has an acute skull
fracture same thing
absolute contraindication
somebody's seizing
it could be absolute
you could make
an argument for being
relative it really
depends on the
clinical situation
Other relative contraindications
include coagulopathies,
if there's a space
-occupying lesion in the
head, and also increased
intracranial pressure.
And of course, always
use common sense. If
something seems like
it's a contraindication,
then don't do it if
you're not comfortable.
before we get into the
anatomy involved with the
techniques we're going to be
doing and the indications and
maybe a case later on I'd
like you to look at this
pause and look at the list
of landmarks here and then
we're going to move on and
I'll show some slides where
you can locate the landmarks
on the slides and and
study them and know it for
when you come into the lab
this is a superior view of
the skull you can locate
some of the landmarks on
the previous slide here
this is a lateral view
of the skull you can
find a lot of the
landmarks from that review
landmark slide here as
well I'd also like to
point out specifically
but not most importantly
Asterion and terion, those
are the ones that are circled.
The other landmarks are
important as well, and the
sutures, but I just want to
point out that the asterion
and terion are the circled
portions where the bones
kind of come together, and
those are important. Asterion
is probably the place where
you're going to feel the
highest amplitude when
you're in the vault contact,
and the tarion is important
clinically as well.
Here is an anterior
view of the skull.
You can locate the
landmarks on the
anterior aspect of the
skull on this slide.
Something I'd like to point
out is the frontonasal
suture versus the nasion.
If you look, the frontonasal
suture is where the two nasal
bones articulate with the
frontal bone, and right in
the midline where the two
nasal bones and the frontal
bone meet, that is nasion.
This slide gives you a good
view of the
posterior landmarks.
Please note the external
occipital protuberance
is a landmark that
we're going to use for
different techniques
throughout this year when we're
talking about cranial
techniques, as well as
the superior nuchal
line. So just be aware of
where those are as well
as the other landmarks
that are listed on the
review landmarks slide.
This slide shows you where
the confluence of sinuses
are. So the venous sinuses
inside the skull, they
all meet up at the confluence
of sinuses, and that's
the little asterisk type
of symbol in both images.
Also note that if you see
on the right-hand image
where the confluence of
sinuses is, you could
see that the skull
there has a little bump.
That's the inion. That's
the external occipital
protuberance. So if you
see where it says for
the right image, it says
right transverse sinus,
right where the little
line that's pointing to the
sinus hits the skull, that's
the external occipital
protuberance. So when we do
some cranial techniques later
on, you're going to be
putting your fingers on that
external occipital
protuberance, or also called the
inia, to help to drain
some of the sinuses. So I'm
pointing that out to you
now so you know where it is.
this slide here is to
remind you that the skull
develops from as the
fetus develops and as
the child grows all the
the cranial bones come
together so you can
see here listed all the
different fontanelles and
for instance where the
anterior fontanelle is
is where bregma will be
where number 9 is on
here posteriorly, that's
where lambda, the landoid
suture is going to be
well that's where lambda
is, landoid suture is number
6 and that follows the
occiput around between the
two parietals but landoid
is at the intersection of
the two parietals and the
occiput that's number nine.
While the last slide
showed the fetal skull,
this is showing the
infant skull at birth, you
can see where those
fontanelles are. They wind
up being bregma, terion,
esterion, and lambda.
So now I'm going to be
talking about the anatomy
specifically related to the
different techniques we're
going to be doing. The
first one's going to be
the chondral decompression.
And here you can see a
picture of the joint between
the occiput and the atlas
where the occipital
condyles articulate with the
condyles of the atlas.
Number 14, there you can
see where the occiput and
the atlas articulate. And
number 7 is pointing to
both the occipital condyles
and the atlas. Notice on
the right-hand side, where
the occipital condyles
articulate with the atlas,
there's an anterior convergence
and a posterior divergence.
So you can really
get the condyles jammed in
in extension, jammed into
the atlas. And that's what
you're going to be treating
when you treat with the
condylar decompression.
Some of the clinical
indications for condylar
decompression are
headache, suckling issues,
colic, neck pain,
low back pain,
plagiocephaly, and there
are other there are many
other indications as well
but these are just some of
the some of the ones
that you may see in your
practice where you can use
the condylar decompression.
As we start to talk about
the cranial lifts. This
slide is showing the ethmoid
notch, and that's going
to be important because
the ethmoid notch is in
the frontal bone, and
that's where the ethmoid
articulates with the frontal
bone. And if there's not
good motion between the
ethmoid and the frontal,
it's going to
impair the drainage
of the frontal and
ethmoid sinuses.
This slide is reminding
you the location of the
frontal, the ethmoid, and
the maxillary sinuses.
Along with sinus
congestion, you can do a
frontal lift to help with
ethmoid restrictions.
You can do a frontal
lift with patients
who have headaches,
who've had trauma or
concussions, patients
with eye complaints,
patients with frontal lobe
mood disorders or executive
function disorders, and
also patients who are
having difficulties with
their sense of smell. The
frontal lift would be
indicated for all of these.
As far as the
nasion spread goes,
you will also do nasion spread
when you're treating sinusitis,
frontal sinusitis,
ethmoid sinusitis.
Patients with post-nasal
drip, this could be helpful.
Again, trauma,
headaches, concussion,
you're going to do
a nasion spread.
Vision and eye complaints,
you could do it.
Anyone with sacral
dysfunctions,
you're going to
treat the nasion.
This is because of
the dural connections
to the ethmoid, and
then you have the
connection of the dural
down to the sacrum.
Patients with
trouble smelling will
also benefit from
an azyon spread.
Now we're going to start
talking about the
parietal lift.
Anatomical considerations
here include the location
of the parietal notch
and the venous sinuses.
So you'll notice that
the parietal notch, the
letter A on the left-hand
side, is in proximity
to the sigmoid sinus,
the transverse sinus, and
the superior petrosal
sinus. A restriction at this
notch can cause a restriction
in the dura around
those venous sinuses
we're talking about here.
also the proximity of the
parietal notch to a sterion
if the parietal notch is
locked up you're going to
have decreased motion at
a sterion so doing a a
parietal lift is going to
help to improve motion and
function of the of the sterion
at the sterion it'll help
improve motion of the
parietal, it's going to help
improve motion with the
temporal, and it's going to
also help improve the dural
strains within the skull.
The transverse sinus and
the tentorium cerebelli
cross near the asterion,
so if you free up, if you
need to free up the
asterion, you can start with
freeing up the parietal
by doing a parietal lift.
So indications for a
parietal lift include
parietal restrictions
that are involved with
headache, ****** and
venous sinus issues,
developmental abnormalities
of all ages, like
plagiocephaly, for
instance, and the different
restrictions I was
talking about earlier.
The nasopharyngeal
physiology is dependent
on the motion of
the ****** bones. If
the bones in the face
are not moving well,
sinuses aren't
going to be able to
drain as well.
There's going to be a
decrease in the quality
of air exchange.
The different various
secretions that need to
secrete aren't going to
be able to do what they're
supposed to do as well
if the bones in the face
are not moving as well
as they are supposed to.
The maxillary sinus
is the most common
site of sinusitis, and
this is because the
opening of the sinus is
high up on the medial
sidewall of the sinus.
The maxilla hangs from the
frontal bone, and it also
has articulations with the
zygoma. So if the frontal is
not moving well, and the
zygoma isn't moving well, then
the maxilla is not going
to be able to move the way
it's supposed to be moving
during primary respiration.
The motion of the zygoma
is very influential in
assisting with the pumping
motion of the maxilla
to enhance the motion
of the maxilla. So if
there's a restriction in
the zygoma, there's going
to be a restriction of
motion with the maxilla.
this slide is showing you
the association of the zygoma
with the maxilla and again
it's reminding you that
the the pump of the maxillary
sinuses is produced by
the movement between the
maxilla and the zygoma so any
restrictions anywhere in
that mechanism is going to
cause a problem with the
drainage of the maxillary sinus
so indications for the
zygomatic lift besides
the the sinusitis and
specifically maxillary
sinusitis would be vision
issues dental issues
and head trauma temporal
disorders and other
other basically
problems of of the head
and or the bones
associated with the zygoma
so here's a case where uh where
cranial manipulation
can be utilized
you have a 28 year old
female who comes to your
office complaining of headaches
associated with stress
at work over the past six
years she's a nurse and
the practice she works
at has been short staffed
for the past five months
the headaches usually occur
on both sides of her
temples when she's at work,
and they're sharp, and she
feels like they're around
her head, and they last
about one to two hours.
The severity ranges from three
to eight out of
ten in severity.
She denies any light sensitivity
or sound sensitivity.
She's not having any
slurred speech or any ******
tingling or numbness. There
are no visual changes.
Rest and ibuprofen
seemed to help the pain.
She's seen a
neurologist who told
her she has tension headaches.
She was told to take
an antidepressant,
but she doesn't want
to take medications.
Biofeedback and cognitive
behavioral therapy
aren't covered by her
insurance, so she really
hasn't been able to
get on board with that.
She's coming to you and wants
to know if OMT is going to
help her past medical and
surgical history are none
she's not on any medications
she has some seasonal
allergies she's denying
any recreational drug use
tobacco use she drinks a
glass of wine a few nights a
week and she does not
exercise her mother has type 2
diabetes and as far as
review systems goes. It's
pretty much negative other
than the headaches. She
denies any dizziness, numbness,
tingling, or weakness.
On exam, her head is normal.
Her eyes are normal.
Her ears are normal.
Her nose mildly
erythematous terminates.
She has some
seasonal allergies.
Her throat, she has a
slight post-nasal drip. Her
neck is supple. There's no
masses or lymphadenopathy.
Neurologically,
cranial nerves 2 through 12 are
grossly intact. She
has a stable gait.
Her upper and lower extremity
motor are 5 out
of 5 bilaterally.
There's no gross sensory
deficits in her upper
lower extremity. Her deep
tendon reflexes for C5,
C6, C7, L4, and S1 are all
2 out of 4 bilaterally.
So as far as the osteopathic
structural exam goes,
her head is forward, her
shoulders were protracted,
there's paratebal muscle spasm,
they're moderately
moderate, and you'll
notice that there's a
lot of moderates written
down here, or moderate,
severe. That's
just saying the severity
of the dysfunction.
She has a bilateral
scapula restriction,
bilateral pectoral
spasm, there's clavicle
dysfunction, there's
bilateral rib 1 dysfunctions,
the trapezen spasm,
there's C2 ERS right, which
is pretty bad, severe.
There's C2 to 5
perivertebral muscle spasm,
which was moderate,
and there's a severe OA
compression, as well as
frontal nasal compression.
So what's going on here?
Well, our assessment
pretty much is that
the patient has a
tension headache and
multiple somatic dysfunctions
in the head, the
cervical region, the
ribs, the thorax, and
the upper extremities.
All right, so what
do you want to do?
Well, this patient most
likely has a tension headache,
so what we'll do is we'll
do some OMT. We'll get her
exercising about 30 minutes
a day to start. we'll
have her also try to do
something to help de-stress.
So maybe recommend some
meditation or prayer or some
other activity that the
patient is willing to do
to help to decrease some
of the stress in her life.
Also, we'll give some
stretches to stretch
out that cervical spine,
stretch out the pecs,
maybe strengthen the
rhomboids. That's, you know,
strengthening the rhomboids,
stretching the pecs, that
kind of goes into a little
bit of an upper cross
syndrome type of thing
that you'll learn about.
As far as the somatic
dysfunctions, you're
going to want to treat
the head, and for that,
you could do a condylar
decompression. There are
other techniques you
could do to treat that
OA compression. The OA joint
is part of the head, so
maybe do a little condylar
decompression there. You
can do a frontal lift,
a zygomatic lift, nasion
spread, get that stuff
moving. You could also treat
any cranial strain patterns
that may have developed.
You can treat the
cervical dysfunctions with
soft tissue, muscle energy,
balanced ligamentous
tension. For the ribs,
you could treat the
thoracic outlet, do a
thoracic outlet release,
maybe do some BLT or other
techniques you've learned.
For the thoracic spine,
maybe do a little soft tissue
for the paraspinal muscles
for the clavicle that's part
of the upper extremity and
the scapula and the pecs
those are all upper extremity
you're going to do some
blt maybe for the clavicle
the scapula you could do a
pectoral traction for the
pecs you could also do some
soft tissue type things
for the scapula as well and
then you're going to tell
your patient to stay hydrated
explain that you might feel
sore the next day or two
that's normal usually in the
younger patients, they feel
sore the next day, maybe
the second day. The older
patients usually takes about
two days at least before
they start to feel sore. So
you just remind the patient
that she may feel sore and
to drink plenty of water.
As far as the stretches
go, I like to have the
patient stretch each
muscle group that I'm
asking them to stretch
about one minute twice a
day. So I would tell her
to stretch her cervical
spine, do three sets
of 20-second stretches
twice a day.
And same thing for the pecs.
And for the rhomboids,
maybe do a little
rhomboid strengthening
exercise. But since
it's strengthening,
they do it once a day
and maybe do it five
or six times a week.
And that's about it. So
thank you for your attention.
By the end of this lab,
not just the lecture, but
by the end of the lab,
you should have reviewed
the cranial strain
patterns and kind of palpated
them on your partner.
You should be able to
discuss indications
and contraindications
of treating
patients with
osteopathic manipulation.
You should also be able
to specifically talk about
the indications for the
condylar decompression and
the lifts, the cranial
lifts we discussed today.
And you should also
be able to perform the
condylar decompression
and the frontal parietal
zygomatic lifts and
the nasion spread.
Make sure you practice, and
we'll see you in
lab. Thank you.